Connecting this full circle,
بتوصيل هذه الدائرة الكاملة،
these capital letters X and Y relate to a random variable.
ترتبط هذه الحروف الكبيرة X وY بالمتغير العشوائي.
This is an abstract idea.
هذه فكرة مجردة.
How much time an individual spends on our website,
كم الوقت الذي يقضيه الفرد على موقعنا،
can take on lots of different values.
قد يأخذ الكثير من القيم المختلفة.
So, this capital letter X is not a number,
لذا، الحرف الكبير X ليس رقمًا،
it's an entire set of possible values.
إنه مجموعة كاملة من القيم المحتملة.
We can think of capital X as a placeholder for any of these possible values.
يمكننا التفكير في الحرف الكبير X على أنه العنصر النائب لأي من هذه القيم المحتملة.
When we look at an individual outcome of our random variable,
عندما تنظرون إلى النتيجة الفردية لمتغيرنا العشوائي،
we signify this with a lower case letter.
نشير إلى هذا بالحروف الصغيرة.
Often the lower case letter has a subscript,
غالبًا ما يكون لدى الحروف الصغيرة رمز سفلي،
that helps us attach notation to each specific value in our dataset.
يساعدنا على إرفاق تدوين لكل قيمة في مجموعة بياناتنا.
For this dataset, we would say the amount of time
بالنسبة لمجموعة البيانات هذه، يمكننا أن نقول أن الوقت
an individual spends on our site is provided by an amount,
الذي يقضيه الفرد على موقعنا يُحدد بالكمية
which we would notate with a capital X.
التي سندونها مع الحرف الكبير X.
The first visitor spends five minutes on the site,
يقضي الزائر الأول خمس دقائق على الموقع،
which we would notate with x1.
وسنرمز له بالرمز x1.
Notice, this is a lowercase x.
لاحظوا أن هذا حرف صغير x.
The second visitor spends 10 minutes on the site,
يقضي الزائر الثاني عشرة دقائق على الموقع،
which we wouldn't notate as x2.
ولن نرمز له بالرمز x2.
Again, since this is an observed value this is a lowercase x.
مرة أخرى، بما أن هذه قيمة ملحوظة، فهذا حرف صغير x.
The labeling could continue until we reach the final visitor in our dataset,
يمكن أن يستمر نظام التسمية حتى نصل إلى الزائر الأخير في مجموعة البيانات،
who we'd called the nth visitor.
وسنطلق عليه اسم الزائر النهائي.
We would label this value as xn.
سنسمي هذه القيمة xn.
Again, this is a lowercase value.
مرة أخرى، هذه قيمة صغيرة.
Notation is an essential tool for us to communicate mathematical ideas.
التدوين هو أداة أساسية لنا لتوصيل الأفكار الرياضية.
We have now discussed the idea that
لقد ناقشنا فكرة أن
capital letters are used as notation for random variables.
الحروف الكبيرة تستخدم كتدوين للمتغيرات العشوائية.
When we observe a particular value of the random variable we use a lowercase letter,
عندما نلاحظ قيمة معينة لمتغير عشوائي، نستخدم الحرف الصغير،
with a subscript that signifies
مع رمز سفلي يشير
the specific value of the random variable we are considering.
إلى القيمة المخصصة للمتغير العشوائي الذي ندرسه.
Notation can be tricky.
يمكن أن يكون التدوين صعبًا
Before we dive deeper, check your understanding.
قبل أن نتابع ونتعمق، تأكدوا من فهمكم.
There are quizzes available in the next module
يوجد اختبارات متاحة في الوحدة النمطية التالية.
to assure you've mastered the concepts we've introduced.
للتأكد من إتقانكم للمفاهيم التي قدمناها.